{
  "translations": {
    "en": {
      "q2":{
        "type": "select",
        "description": "Consider this grammar:<br/>$S \\rightarrow aB \\mid bA$<br>$A \\rightarrow aA$<br>$B \\rightarrow Sa$<br>$C \\rightarrow cBc \\mid a$<br> What can you say about this grammar?",
        "question": "First think about the variable $C$. Can we reach variable $C$ from $S$ directly or indirectly?",
        "answer": "No",
        "choices": ["No","Yes"]
      },
      "q3":{
        "type": "select",
        "description": "Consider this grammar:<br/>$S \\rightarrow aB \\mid bA$<br>$A \\rightarrow aA$<br>$B \\rightarrow Sa$<br>$C \\rightarrow cBc \\mid a$<br> What can you say about this grammar?",
        "question": "Is $C$ a useful or useless variable?",
        "answer": "useless",
        "choices": ["useless","useful"]
      },
      "q4":{
        "type": "select",
        "description": "Consider this grammar:<br/>$S \\rightarrow aB \\mid bA$<br>$A \\rightarrow aA$<br>$B \\rightarrow Sa$<br>$C \\rightarrow cBc \\mid a$<br> What can you say about this grammar?",
        "question": "Should we keep the variable $C$?",
        "answer": "No, because it is useless variable.",
        "choices": ["Yes, it might be useful later.", "No, because it is useless variable."]
      },
      "q5":{
        "type": "select",
        "description": "Here is the grammar after removing $C$ and its associated productions:<br/>$S \\rightarrow aB \\mid bA$<br>$A \\rightarrow aA$<br>$B \\rightarrow Sa$<br/>What can we say about this grammar?",
        "question": "Can you generate any string from this grammar?",
        "answer": "No",
        "choices": ["Yes","No"]
      },
      "q6":{
        "type": "true/false",
        "description": "Consider this grammar:<br/>$S \\rightarrow aB \\mid bA$<br>$A \\rightarrow aA$<br>$B \\rightarrow Sa$<br/>What can you say about this grammar?",
        "question": "$A$ , $S$, and $B$ are useless variables since they can’t derive a string of terminals.",
        "answer": "True",
        "choices": []
      },
      "q7":{
        "type": "true/false",
        "description": "Theorem: (useless productions) Let $G$ be a CFG. Then there exists $G'$ that does not contain any useless variables or productions such that $L(G) = L(G')$.",
        "question": "Removing useless productions will affect the grammar's language.",
        "answer": "False",
        "choices": []
      },
      "q9":{
        "type": "select",
        "description": "We have seen two types of useless productions.<br/>1. Productions that are unreachable. These are the productions that we can not reach from the start variable.",
        "question": "In this grammar:<br/>$S \\rightarrow aB \\mid bA$<br>$A \\rightarrow aA$<br>$B \\rightarrow Sa$<br>$C \\rightarrow cBc \\mid a$<br>Which variable is unreachable?",
        "answer": "C",
        "choices": ["A","S","C","B"]
      },
      "q10":{
        "type": "select",
        "description": "We have seen two types of useless productions.<br/>1. Productions that are unreachable. These are the productions that we can not reach from the start variable.<br/>2. Productions that are nonterminating, meaning that these production will keep looping with the same/other productions without termination (so, no strings will come out of these productions).",
        "question": "In this grammar:<br/>$S \\rightarrow aB \\mid bA$<br>$A \\rightarrow aA$<br>$B \\rightarrow Sa$<br>$C \\rightarrow cBc \\mid a$<br/>Which variables are nonterminating?",
        "answer": ["A","S","B"],
        "choices": ["A","S","C","B"]
      },
      "q14":{
        "type": "select",
        "description": "An algorithm to remove useless productions.<br/>Let $G=(V,T,S,P)$.<br/>1. Compute $V_1 =$ {Variables that can derive strings of terminals}<br/>$\\quad 1.\\ V_1 = \\emptyset$<br/>$\\quad 2.$ Repeat until no more variables are added:<br/>$\\quad\\quad$ For every $A \\in V$ with $A\\rightarrow x_1x_2\\ldots x_n$, $x_i \\in (T^* \\cup V_1)$, add $A$ to $V_1$",
        "question": "For grammar on the left, what is the initial value for $V_1$?",
        "answer": "$\\emptyset$",
        "choices": ["A","S","C","B","$\\emptyset$","E","D"]
      },
      "q15":{
        "type": "select",
        "description": "An algorithm to remove useless productions.<br/>Let $G=(V,T,S,P)$.<br/>1. Compute $V_1 =$ {Variables that can derive strings of terminals}<br/>$\\quad 1.\\ V_1 = \\emptyset$<br/>$\\quad 2.$ Repeat until no more variables are added:<br/>$\\quad\\quad$ For every $A \\in V$ with $A\\rightarrow x_1x_2\\ldots x_n$, $x_i \\in (T^* \\cup V_1)$, add $A$ to $V_1$.<br/><br/>In other words, on each iteration, add all variables whose productions only terminals and variables already in $V_1$.",
        "question": "What should we add to $V_1$ in the fist iteration?",
        "answer": ["B","C","E"],
        "choices": ["A","S","C","B","$\\emptyset$","E","D"]
      },
      "q16":{
        "type": "select",
        "description": "An algorithm to remove useless productions.<br/>Let $G=(V,T,S,P)$.<br/>1. Compute $V_1 =$ {Variables that can derive strings of terminals}<br/>$\\quad 1.\\ V_1 = \\emptyset$<br/>$\\quad 2.$ Repeat until no more variables are added:<br/>$\\quad\\quad$ For every $A \\in V$ with $A\\rightarrow x_1x_2\\ldots x_n$, $x_i \\in (T^* \\cup V_1)$, add $A$ to $V_1$.<br/><br/>In other words, on each iteration, add all variables whose productions only terminals and variables already in $V_1$.",
        "question": "What should we add to $V_1$ in the next iteration?",
        "answer": ["S","D"],
        "choices": ["A","S","C","B","$\\emptyset$","E","D"]
      },
      "q17":{
        "type": "select",
        "description": "An algorithm to remove useless productions.<br/>Let $G=(V,T,S,P)$.<br/>1. Compute $V_1 =$ {Variables that can derive strings of terminals}<br/>$\\quad 1.\\ V_1 = \\emptyset$<br/>$\\quad 2.$ Repeat until no more variables are added:<br/>$\\quad\\quad$ For every $A \\in V$ with $A\\rightarrow x_1x_2\\ldots x_n$, $x_i \\in (T^* \\cup V_1)$, add $A$ to $V_1$.<br/><br/>In other words, on each iteration, add all variables whose productions only terminals and variables already in $V_1$.",
        "question": "What should we add to $V_1$ in the next iteration?",
        "answer": "$\\emptyset$",
        "choices": ["A","S","C","B","$\\emptyset$","E","D"]
      },
      "q18":{
        "type": "select",
        "description": "An algorithm to remove useless productions.<br/>Let $G=(V,T,S,P)$.<br/>1. Compute $V_1 =$ {Variables that can derive strings of terminals}<br/>$\\quad 1.\\ V_1 = \\emptyset$<br/>$\\quad 2.$ Repeat until no more variables are added:<br/>$\\quad\\quad$ For every $A \\in V$ with $A\\rightarrow x_1x_2\\ldots x_n$, $x_i \\in (T^* \\cup V_1)$, add $A$ to $V_1$.<br/><br/>In other words, on each iteration, add all variables whose productions only terminals and variables already in $V_1$.",
        "question": "Should we continue?",
        "answer": "No because we did not add any variables in the last iteration",
        "choices": ["Yes", "No because we did not add any variables in the last iteration"]
      },
      "q19":{
        "type": "select",
        "description": "An algorithm to remove useless productions.<br/>Let $G=(V,T,S,P)$.<br/>1. Compute $V_1 =$ {Variables that can derive strings of terminals}<br/>$\\quad 1.\\ V_1 = \\emptyset$<br/>$\\quad 2.$ Repeat until no more variables are added:<br/>$\\quad\\quad$ For every $A \\in V$ with $A\\rightarrow x_1x_2\\ldots x_n$, $x_i \\in (T^* \\cup V_1)$, add $A$ to $V_1$.<br/>$\\quad 3.\\ P_1=$ all productions in $P$ whose RHS contains only $(V_1\\cup T)^*$.",
        "question": "Which productions should be added to $P_1$?",
        "answer": ["$S\\rightarrow aB$", "$B\\rightarrow Sa$", "$B\\rightarrow b$", "$C\\rightarrow cBc$", "$C\\rightarrow a$", "$D\\rightarrow bCb$", "$E\\rightarrow b$"],
        "choices": ["$S\\rightarrow aB$", "$S\\rightarrow bA$", "$A\\rightarrow aA$", "$B\\rightarrow Sa$", "$B\\rightarrow b$", "$C\\rightarrow cBc$", "$C\\rightarrow a$", "$D\\rightarrow bCb$", "$E\\rightarrow Aa$", "$E\\rightarrow b$"]
      },
      "q20":{
        "type": "select",
        "description": "The resulting grammar $G_1=(V_1,T,S,P_1)$ has no variables that can’t derive strings.",
        "question": "Did we finish removing useless productions?",
        "answer": "No",
        "choices": ["No", "Yes"],
        "correctFeedback": ["There are variables that we cannot reach in a derivation."],
        "incorrectFeedback": ["Can we derive every one of the variables still in the set of production rules?"]
      },
      "q22":{
        "type": "select",
        "description": "An algorithm to remove useless productions.<br/>Let $G=(V,T,S,P)$<br/>2. Remove unreachable productions by using a Variable Dependency Graph (VDG)<br/>First draw a node for every variable.",
        "question": "How many nodes does the VDG have?",
        "answer": "5",
        "choices": ["1", "2","3","4","5","6","7"]
      },
      "q23":{
        "type": "select",
        "description": "Removing useless production algorithm<br/>Let $G=(V,T,S,P)$<br/>2. Remove unreachable productions by using Variable Dependency Graph (VDG)<br/>Draw a node for every variable.<br/>For production $A\\rightarrow xBy$, draw edge $A \\rightarrow B$.",
        "question": "What is the edge for the highlighted production?",
        "answer": "S to B",
        "choices": ["S to B", "B to S", "C to B", "D to C"]
      },
      "q24":{
        "type": "select",
        "description": "Removing useless production algorithm<br/>Let $G=(V,T,S,P)$<br/>2. Remove unreachable productions by using Variable Dependency Graph (VDG)<br/>Draw a node for every variable.<br/>For production $A\\rightarrow xBy$, draw an edge $A \\rightarrow B$.",
        "question": "What is the edge for the highlighted production",
        "answer": "B to S",
        "choices": ["S to B", "B to S", "C to B", "D to C"]
      },
      "q25":{
        "type": "select",
        "description": "Removing useless production algorithm<br/>Let $G=(V,T,S,P)$<br/>2. Remove unreachable productions by using Variable Dependency Graph (VDG)<br/>Draw a node for every variable.<br/>For production $A\\rightarrow xBy$, draw an edge $A \\rightarrow B$.",
        "question": "What is the edge for the highlighted production",
        "answer": "C to B",
        "choices": ["S to B", "B to S", "C to B", "D to C"]
      },
      "q26":{
        "type": "select",
        "description": "Removing useless production algorithm<br/>Let $G=(V,T,S,P)$<br/>2. Remove unreachable productions by using Variable Dependency Graph (VDG)<br/>Draw a node for every variable.<br/>For production $A\\rightarrow xBy$, draw an edge $A \\rightarrow B$.",
        "question": "What is the edge for the highlighted production",
        "answer": "D to C",
        "choices": ["S to B", "B to S", "C to B", "D to C"]
      },
      "q27":{
        "type": "select",
        "description": "Removing useless production algorithm<br/>Let $G=(V,T,S,P)$<br/>2. Remove unreachable productions by using Variable Dependency Graph (VDG)<br/>Draw a node for every variable.<br/>For production $A\\rightarrow xBy$, draw an edge $A \\rightarrow B$.<br/>Remove productions for any $V$ that has no path from $S$ to $V$ in the dependency graph.",
        "question": "Which variables must be removed?",
        "answer": ["E", "C", "D"],
        "choices": ["E", "S", "B", "C", "D"]
      }
    }
  }
}
